19 chapter 20 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 20 Joe Green Joe Green went on very well; he
learned quickly, and was so attentive and careful that John began to trust him in
many things; but as I have said, he was small of his age, and it was seldom that
he was allowed to exercise either Ginger or me; but it so happened one morning
that John was out with Justice in the luggage cart, and the master wanted a
note to be taken immediately to a gentleman's house, about 3 mil distant,
and sent his orders for Joe to saddle me and take it, adding the caution that he
was to ride steadily.
The note was delivered, and we were quietly returning when we came to the
brick field Here we saw a cart heavily laden with bricks; the wheels had stuck
fast in the stiff mud of some deep rats and the carter was shouting and flogging
the two horses unmercifully. Joe pulled up. It was a sad sight. There were the two horses
straining and struggling with all their might to drag the cart out, but they
could not move it; the sweat streamed from their legs and flanks the sides
heaved, and every muscle was strained, while the man, fiercely pulling at the
head of the foror swore and lashed most brutally. “Hold hard,” said Joe; “don't go on
flogging the horses like that; the wheels are so stuck that they cannot move the
cart.” The man took no heed, but went on lashing. “Stop pra stop!” said Joe. “I'll help
you to lighten the cart; they can't move it now.” “Mind your own business, you impudent
young rascal, and I'll mind mine!” The man was in a towering passion and the worse
for drink, and laid on the whip again. Joe turned my head, and the next
moment we were going at a round gallop towards the house of the master brick
maker I cannot say if John would have approved of our pace, but Joe and I were
both of one mind, and so angry that we could not have gone
slower. The house stood close by the roadside. Joe knocked at the door, and
shouted hello Is Mr. Clay at home?” The door was open and Mr. Clay himself came
out hello young man! You seem in a hurry; any orders from the squire this
morning?” “No, Mr. Clay, but there's a fellow in your Brickyard flogging two horses to
death. I told him to stop, and he wouldn't; I said I'd help him to lighten the cart,
and he wouldn't; so I have come to tell you. Pray, sir, go.” Joe's voice shook with excitement.
“Thank you myad said the man, running in for his hat; then pausing for a moment,
“Will you give evidence of what you saw if I should bring the fellow up before a
magistrate?” “That I will,” said Joe I'm glad too.” The man was gone, and we were on our
way home at a smart trot. “Why, what's the matter with you, Joe?
You look angry all over,” said Jon as the boy flung himself from the saddle. “I am
angry all over, I can tell you,” said the boy, and then in hurried, excited words he
told all that had happened. Joe was usually such a quiet, gentle little fellow that it was
wonderful to see him so roused. “Right, Joe! you did right, my boy,
whether the fellow gets a summons or not.
Many folks would have ridden by and said it was not their business to interfere.
Now I say that with cruelty and oppression it is everybody's business to
interfere when they see it; you did right, my boy.” Joe was quite calm by this time, and
proud that Jon approved of him, and cleaned out my feet and rubbed me down
with a firmer hand than usual. They were just going home to
dinner when the footman came down to the stable to say that Joe was wanted
directly in master's private room; there was a man brought up for ill using
horses, and Joe's evidence was wanted. The boy flushed up to his
forehead, and his eyes sparkled. “They shall have it,” said he. “Put yourself a bit
straight,” said Jon Joe gave a pull at his necktie and a twitch at his jacket, and
was off in a moment. Our master being one of the county magistrates, cases were often
brought to him to settle, or say what should be done. In the stable we heard no
more for some time, as it was the men's dinner hour, but when Joe came next into
the stable I saw he was in high spirits; he gave me a good-natured slap, and said,
“We won't see such things done, will we, old fellow?” We heard afterward that he had given his
evidence so clearly, and the horses were in such an exhausted state, bearing marks
of such brutal usage, that the carter was committed to take his trial, and might
possibly be sentenced to two or 3 months in prison. It was wonderful what a change
had come over Joe JN laughed, and said he had grown an inch taller in that week,
and I believe he had. He was just as kind and gentle as before, but there was more
purpose and determination in all that he did— —as if he had jumped at once from a
boy into a man end of chapter